<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-03-23T22:11:07+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Victorian Naturalist</title><subtitle>A blog about nineteenth century Britain and natural history</subtitle><author><name>Ali Hatapçı</name></author><entry><title type="html">Science on Local, Region, and National Scales: Geographies of Natural History in the mid- to late Victorian England</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/oral%20presentations/abstract-mans/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science on Local, Region, and National Scales: Geographies of Natural History in the mid- to late Victorian England" /><published>2022-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/oral%20presentations/abstract-mans</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/oral%20presentations/abstract-mans/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Abstract of my presentation to be given during the <a href="https://ams.hypotheses.org/2278">Colloquium “Amateurs in Science: a history from below”</a> organised as part of the <a href="https://ams.hypotheses.org/">AmateurS</a> project, 5-7 September 2022.</strong></p>

<p>From the 1780s, the literary and philosophical societies (Lit and Phils) emerged as pioneers of science culture in provincial England. Whilst their high subscription fees secured their privileged status as the preserve of the upper and middle-class socialisation, their intellectual eclecticism spanning from literature to the discussions on evolution helped them survive throughout the nineteenth-century. Studies on the Lit and Phils have been dominated by the case studies on the those established in the north of England. As a result, much of our understanding of these associations which became the hallmark of Victorian civic pride and culture has been shaped by the peculiarities of this industrial region where the largest networks of professional scientists appeared in the late nineteenth-century England. In this paper, however, I examine three Lit and Phils in the Midlands, namely, those of Birmingham (1876-1894), Leicester (1835- ) and Nottingham (1865-1883). The three towns and their Lit and Phils provide recognizably different urban structures and actors to re-examine our understanding of the practice and organisation of science in Victorian England. By investigating the self-identification of these provincial scientific associations vis-à-vis scientific research, notably fieldwork, and the self-assigned role within the urban hierarchy of scientific institutions, as well as their attitude and relation to professionalisation of science, I present a novel view on the Lit and Phils and on the organisation of science in urban England in Victorian period.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ali Hatapçı</name></author><category term="oral presentations" /><category term="abstract" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract of my presentation to be given during the Colloquium “Amateurs in Science: a history from below” organised as part of the AmateurS project, 5-7 September 2022.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Urban hierarchies of science in mid- to late Victorian England: The literary and philosophical societies in the Midlands</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/oral%20presentations/abstract-cak/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Urban hierarchies of science in mid- to late Victorian England: The literary and philosophical societies in the Midlands" /><published>2022-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/oral%20presentations/abstract-cak</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/oral%20presentations/abstract-cak/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Abstract of my presentation to be given during the Journées des Jeunes Chercheur.se.s du <a href="http://koyre.ehess.fr/">Centre Alexandre Koyré</a> on 19 May 2022.</strong></p>

<p>From the 1780s, the literary and philosophical societies (Lit and Phils) emerged as pioneers of science culture in provincial England. Whilst their high subscription fees secured their privileged status as the preserve of the upper and middle-class socialisation, their intellectual eclecticism spanning from literature to the discussions on evolution helped them survive throughout the nineteenth-century. Studies on the Lit and Phils have been dominated by the case studies on the those established in the north of England. As a result, much of our understanding of these associations which became the hallmark of Victorian civic pride and culture has been shaped by the peculiarities of this industrial region where the largest networks of professional scientists appeared in the late nineteenth-century England. In this paper, however, I examine three Lit and Phils in the Midlands, namely, those of Birmingham (1876-1894), Leicester (1835- ) and Nottingham (1865-1883). The three towns and their Lit and Phils provide recognizably different urban structures and actors to re-examine our understanding of the practice and organisation of science in Victorian England. By investigating the self-identification of these provincial scientific associations vis-à-vis scientific research, notably fieldwork, and the self-assigned role within the urban hierarchy of scientific institutions, as well as their attitude and relation to professionalisation of science, I present a novel view on the Lit and Phils and on the organisation of science in urban England in Victorian period.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ali Hatapçı</name></author><category term="oral presentations" /><category term="abstract" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract of my presentation to be given during the Journées des Jeunes Chercheur.se.s du Centre Alexandre Koyré on 19 May 2022.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Note-taking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/historian's%20toolkit/note-taking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note-taking" /><published>2022-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/historian&apos;s%20toolkit/note-taking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/historian&apos;s%20toolkit/note-taking/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://webstockreview.net/images/important-clipart-note-taking-2.png" alt="" />
Whether you are a student or an office worker, note-taking is an important activity,<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and too often, it is taken for granted. For historians, however, it is an essential part of the job. The renowned historian of early modern England, <a href="https://www.asc.ox.ac.uk/person/sir-keith-thomas">Sir Keith Vivan Thomas</a>’s unpretentious and revealing article in <em>London Review of Books</em><sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> provides insights into the importance and the evolution of this essential activity to the historians. If the books and articles that come off the press are the end-products of long and painstaking process of research, the notes of the historian are the embodiment of both the method and pieces of the result which are processed by the historian. On the other hand, Thomas writes that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It never helps historians to say too much about their working methods. For just as the conjuror’s magic disappears if the audience knows how the trick is done, so the credibility of scholars can be sharply diminished if readers learn everything about how exactly their books came to be written. Only too often, such revelations dispel the impression of fluent, confident omniscience; instead, they suggest that histories are concocted by error-prone human beings who patch together the results of incomplete research in order to construct an account whose rhetorical power will, they hope, compensate for gaps in the argument and deficiencies in the evidence.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To reduce the gaps as much as possible, good historians need to <strong>immerse</strong> themselves in the period they study. Taking a larger view than their very narrowly defined topic, they try to read (and in the case of modern history listen and watch) the products of the period of their study as much as possible. As Thomas suggests, this immersion which comes through an open-minded, non-restrictive way of “looking at everything…remotely relevant” to the subject might suggest that the historical method is a sort of “<em><strong>omnium gatherum</strong></em>” of historical material.</p>

<p>While this omnivorousness helps the historian to speak with authority and gather a large number of notes, the problem of putting them together in a coherent and analytical work appears as the problem. Thomas writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is possible to take too many notes; the task of sorting, filing and assimilating them can take for ever, so that nothing gets written.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>How to overcome this difficulty of sorting out the notes and putting them together in a coherent argumentative work?</p>

<p>Keith Thomas in his article points out to the technology that has in the last two decades become indispensable for historians. But the difficulty persists for those whose bulk of notes are so huge and so difficult to put together on a computer program. Thomas sighs that</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But it is far too late to think of transferring this accumulation onto some electronic database. When I look at my cellar, stuffed with cardboard boxes and dog-eared folders, and littered with loose slips which have broken free from overstuffed envelopes, I envy my colleagues who travel light, with their laptops and digital cameras. But, as Gibbon said, where error is irreparable, repentance is useless.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>During my master’s but especially in the beginning of my phd, I experimented with different tools and methods of taking notes. At that time, I got hold of Umberto Eco’s <em>How to Write a Thesis</em> (1977, 1985, 2012), where Eco advises using index cards to keep track of the notes and to relate the new cards to the old ones through several methods.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> Although I tried this method, I could not continue it. Apart from the difficulty of organising the cards, their fragility and insecurity in my student’s apartment did not seem very feasible. So, I decided rather to try to mimic the index cards by using more reliable, durable, and secure tools. Enter Microsoft Word, Google sheets and document, and finally OneNote.</p>

<p>I finished my phd thesis thanks to OneNote. Its hierarchical layout (notebooks&gt;sections&gt;pages&gt;2 levels of subpages&gt;paragraphs) provides some sense of organisation. Added to this is the full text search function intrinsic to any digital note-taking tool.</p>

<p>As a fresh phd with an ambition to continue my career as a historian, I began to look for tools to improve my arsenal. That is when I came across many tools which provide many more functions and much more flexibility than the linear hierarchy offered by OneNote. The wiki type note-taking tools have been available for more than a decade (e.g. <a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org-mode</a>, <a href="https://tiddlywiki.com/">Tiddylywiki</a>, <a href="https://vimwiki.github.io/">Vimwiki</a>). However incredible they are in providing a plethora of options to create links between the notes, both of these tools require a steep learning curve and determination. Newbies can be easily discouraged and begin to question the priority of learning the functions of these tools and taking notes.</p>

<p>More recently, however, there has been a boom in the number of software which provide similar or better functions and better user experience. <a href="https://roamresearch.com/">RoamResearch</a>, which brands itself as “A note-taking tool for networked thought” was until recently a led the market. Despite its alleged ease of use (I didn’t try it myself), it is a very expensive online service with a monthly subscription of $15.</p>

<p>Luckily there are also cheaper (essentially free) and future-proof tools which provide similar functions and better control over the ownership of your notes. My favourite one is <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>, which brands itself as “A second brain,
for you, forever”. Obsidian is basically free if you don’t want to buy their file synchronisation service. In any case, you can synchronise your notes by placing your Obsidian project in your cloud service of choice such as GoogleDrive, OneDrive or Dropbox. With Obisidan, you are in control of your notes, their ownership rests with you as they are always on your computer or on your own cloud service. Furthermore, Obsidian uses non-proprietary markdown files which can be read both by humans and computers without a fear of an enterprise going down or service being terminated. In other words, your notes are future-proof! As a result, even if one day Obsidian goes under or you decide to use another tool, you can still make use of your notes. Although there are differences between them and moving from one to another is not straightforward <a href="https://zettlr.com/">Zettlr</a> can be another option. It has inherent bibliography support and its function to export notes in different file formats such as docx and pdf has made it a significant contended among academics. Zettlr is entirely free and brands itself as “a markdown editor for the 21st century”.</p>

<p>All in all, in modern day, whether you are a historian or any other knowledge worker, we are required to manage an immense amount of information. The democratisation of these excellent tools, both free and easy-to-use, should not be taken for granted. These tools probably change our workflows and methods. In my experience, Obsidian is the winner although I have a couple of other still installed on my computer, notably Zettlr.</p>

<h3 id="references"><strong>References</strong></h3>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>For a set of advices on note-taking (mostly in the classroom) see <a href="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/umberto-eco-how-to-write-a-thesis/">https://academicresourcecenter.harvard.edu/note-taking</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Keith Thomas, “Working Methods.” <a href="https://www.lrb.co.uk/the-paper/v32/n11/keith-thomas/diary"><em>London Review of Books</em> (2010) 32 (11)</a>. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Umberto Eco, <em>How to Write a Thesis</em>, MIT Press, 2012. For an excerpt from Eco’s book see <a href="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/umberto-eco-how-to-write-a-thesis/">https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/umberto-eco-how-to-write-a-thesis/</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Ali Hatapçı</name></author><category term="historian&apos;s toolkit" /><category term="research tools" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Whether you are a student or an office worker, note-taking is an important activity,1 and too often, it is taken for granted. For historians, however, it is an essential part of the job. The renowned historian of early modern England, Sir Keith Vivan Thomas’s unpretentious and revealing article in London Review of Books2 provides insights into the importance and the evolution of this essential activity to the historians. If the books and articles that come off the press are the end-products of long and painstaking process of research, the notes of the historian are the embodiment of both the method and pieces of the result which are processed by the historian. On the other hand, Thomas writes that For a set of advices on note-taking (mostly in the classroom) see https://academicresourcecenter.harvard.edu/note-taking &#8617; Keith Thomas, “Working Methods.” London Review of Books (2010) 32 (11). &#8617;]]></summary></entry></feed>